<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prosopopoia, or, Mother Hubberds tale by Edm. Sp. ; dedicated to the right honourable, the Lady Compton and Mountegle.</title>
            <author>Spenser, Edmund, 1552?-1599.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23087.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2337</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23281978</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23281978</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26504</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26504)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1803:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prosopopoia, or, Mother Hubberds tale by Edm. Sp. ; dedicated to the right honourable, the Lady Compton and Mountegle.</title>
                  <author>Spenser, Edmund, 1552?-1599.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.L. and are sold by G. Lathum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1628?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Imprint date suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>In double columns.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-C².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
               <p>IH<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>S</p>
            </figure>
            <p>By <hi>Edm. Sp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dedicated to the right Honourable, the Lady <hi>Compton</hi> and
<hi>Mountegle.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>dragon rampant</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> and are ſold by <hi>G.
Lathum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26504:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26504:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, the Lady <hi>Compton</hi> and
<hi>Mountegle.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST faire and vertuous Lady; hauing ſought opportunitie by
ſome good meanes to make knowne to your Ladiſhip, the humble affection and
faithfull dutie, which I haue alwaies profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and am bound to beare to
that Houſe, from whence ye ſpring; I haue at length found occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to
remember the ſame, by making a ſimple preſent to you of theſe my idle
labours; which hauing long ſithens compoſed in the raw con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of my
youth, I lately among other papers lighted vpon, and was by others, which liked
the ſame, moued to ſet them forth. Simple is the deuice, and the
compoſition meane, yet carrieth ſome delight, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the rather, becauſe
of the ſimplicitie and meanneſſe thus perſonated. The ſame I
beſeech your Ladiſhip take in good part, as a pledge of that profeſſion
which I haue made to you; and keepe with you, vntill with ſome other more
worthy labour, I doe redeeme it out of your hands, and diſcharge my vtmoſt
duetie. Till then, wiſhing your Ladiſhip all increaſe of honour and
happineſſe, I humbly take leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your La. euer</hi> humbly;
Ed. Sp.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26504:3"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="fable">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:26504:3"/>
            <head>PROSOPOPOIA: OR <hi>Mother Hubberds Tale.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IT was the month, in which the righteous Maide,</l>
               <l>That for diſdaine of ſinfull worlds vpbraide,</l>
               <l>Fled back to heauen, whence ſhe was firſt conceiued,</l>
               <l>Into her ſiluer bower the Sunne receiued;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And the hot <hi>Syrian</hi> dog on him awayting,</l>
               <l>After the chafed Lions cruell bayting,</l>
               <l>Corrupted had th' ayre with his noyſome breath,</l>
               <l>And pour'd on th' earth plague, peſtilence, and death.</l>
               <l>Amongſt the reſt, a wicked maladie</l>
               <l>Raign'd emongſt men, that many did to die,</l>
               <l>Depriu'd of ſenſe and ordinary reaſon;</l>
               <l>That it to Leaches ſeemed ſtrange and geaſon.</l>
               <l>My fortune was mongſt many other moe,</l>
               <l>To be partaker of their common woe;</l>
               <l>And my weake body ſet on fire with griefe,</l>
               <l>Was robd of reſt, and naturall reliefe.</l>
               <l>In this ill plight, there came to viſite mee</l>
               <l>Some friends, who ſorry my ſad caſe to ſee,</l>
               <l>Began to comfort me in chearefull wiſe,</l>
               <l>And meanes of gladſome ſolace to deuiſe.</l>
               <l>But ſeeing kindly ſleepe refuſe to doe</l>
               <l>His office, and my feeble eyes forgoe,</l>
               <l>They ſought my troubled ſenſe how to deceaue</l>
               <l>With talke, that might vnquiet fancies reaue;</l>
               <l>And ſitting all on ſeats about me round,</l>
               <l>With pleaſant tales (fit for that idle ſtound)</l>
               <l>They caſt in courſe to waſte the wearie howres:</l>
               <l>Some tolde of Ladies, and their Paramours;</l>
               <l>Some of braue Knights, and their renowned Squires;</l>
               <l>Some of the Faeries, and their ſtrange attires;</l>
               <l>And ſome of Giants, hard to be belieued,</l>
               <l>That the delight thereof me much relieued.</l>
               <l>Amongſt the reſt, a good old woman was,</l>
               <l>Hight Mother <hi>Hubberd,</hi> who did far ſurpaſſe</l>
               <l>The reſt in honeſt mirth, that ſeem'd her well:</l>
               <l>She when her turne was come her tale to tell,</l>
               <l>Told of a ſtrange adventure, that betided</l>
               <l>Betwixt the Foxe and th' Ape by him miſguided;</l>
               <l>The which for that my ſenſe it greatly pleaſed,</l>
               <l>All were my ſpirit heauie and diſeaſed,</l>
               <l>Ile write in termes, as ſhee the ſame did ſay,</l>
               <l>So well as I her words remember may.</l>
               <l>No Muſes ayde me needs heere-to to call;</l>
               <l>Baſe is the ſtyle, and matter meane withall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Whylome (ſaid ſhe) before the world was ciuill,</l>
               <l>The Foxe and th' Ape diſliking of their euill</l>
               <l>And hard eſtate, determined to ſeeke</l>
               <l>Their fortunes farre abroad, lyeke with lyeke<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For both were crafty and vnhappy witted;</l>
               <l>Two fellowes might no where be better fitted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Foxe, that firſt this cauſe of griefe did finde,</l>
               <l>Gan firſt thus plain his caſe with words vnkinde.</l>
               <l>Neighbour Ape, and my Goſſip eke beſide</l>
               <l>(Both two ſure bands in friendſhip to be ti'de)</l>
               <l>To whom may I more truſtily complaine</l>
               <l>The euill plight, that doth me ſore conſtraine,</l>
               <l>And hope thereof to finde due remedy?</l>
               <l>Heare then my paine and inward agonie.</l>
               <l>Thus many yeeres I now haue ſpent and worne,</l>
               <l>In meane regard, and baſeſt fortunes ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Dooing my Country ſeruice as I might,</l>
               <l>No leſſe I dare ſay then the proudeſt weight;</l>
               <l>And ſtill I hoped to be vp aduaunced,</l>
               <l>For my good parts; but ſtill it hath miſchaunced.</l>
               <l>Now therefore that no longer hope I ſee,</l>
               <l>But froward fortune ſtill to follow me,</l>
               <l>And loſels lifted high, where I did looke,</l>
               <l>I meane to turne the next leafe of the booke:</l>
               <l>Yet ere that any way I doe betake,</l>
               <l>I meane my Goſſip priuy firſt to make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah! my deare Goſſip (anſwer'd then the Ape)</l>
               <l>Deepely doe your ſad words my wits awhape,</l>
               <l>Both for becauſe your griefe doth great appeare,</l>
               <l>And eke becauſe my ſelfe am touched neare<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For I likewiſe haue waſted much good time,</l>
               <l>Still wayting to preferment vp to clime,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt others alwaies haue before me ſtept,</l>
               <l>And from my beard the fat away haue ſwept;</l>
               <l>That now vnto deſpaire I gin to growe,</l>
               <l>And meane for better winde about to throwe.</l>
               <l>Therefore to me, my truſtie friend, aread</l>
               <l>Thy counſell: Two is better then one head.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Certes (ſaid he) I meane me to diſguize</l>
               <l>In ſome ſtrange habit, after vncouth wize,</l>
               <l>Or like a Pilgrim, or a Lymiter,</l>
               <l>Or like a Gipſen, or a Iuggeler,</l>
               <l>And ſo to wander to the worldes end,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke my fortune, where I may it mend:</l>
               <l>For worſe then that I haue I cannot meet.</l>
               <l>Wide is the world I wote, and euery ſtreet</l>
               <l>Is full of fortunes, and adventures ſtrange,</l>
               <l>Continually ſubiect vnto change.</l>
               <l>Say my faire brother now, if this deuice</l>
               <l>Doe like you, or may you to like entice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Surely (ſaid th' Ape) it likes me wondrous well;</l>
               <l>And would ye not poore fellowſhip expell,</l>
               <l>My ſelfe would offer you t' accompany</l>
               <l>In this adventures chauncefull ieopardie.</l>
               <l>For to wexe olde at home in idleneſſe,</l>
               <l>Is diſaduentrous, and quite fortuneleſſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:26504:4"/> Abroad where change is, good may gotten
be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Foxe was glad, and quickly did agree:</l>
               <l>So both reſolu'd the morrow next enſuing,</l>
               <l>So ſoone as day appear'd to peoples viewing,</l>
               <l>On their intended iourney to proceed;</l>
               <l>And over night, what-ſo thereto did need,</l>
               <l>Each did prepare in readineſſe to bee.</l>
               <l>The morrow next, ſo ſoone as one might ſee</l>
               <l>Light out of heauens windowes forth to looke,</l>
               <l>Both their habiliments vnto them tooke,</l>
               <l>And put themſelues (a Gods name) on their way:</l>
               <l>When-as the Ape beginning well to wey</l>
               <l>This hard adventure, thus began t' adviſe;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now read Sir Reynold, as ye be right wiſe,</l>
               <l>What courſe yee weene is beſt for vs to take,</l>
               <l>That for our ſelues we may a liuing make.</l>
               <l>Whether ſhall we profeſſe ſome trade or skill?</l>
               <l>Or ſhall we vary our deuice at will,</l>
               <l>Euen as new occaſion appeares?</l>
               <l>Or ſhall we tie our ſelues for certaine yeeres,</l>
               <l>To any ſeruice, or to any place?</l>
               <l>For it behoues ere that into the race</l>
               <l>We enter, to reſolue firſt hereupon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſurely brother (ſaid the Foxe anon)</l>
               <l>Ye haue this matter motioned in ſeaſon:</l>
               <l>For euery thing that is begun with reaſon</l>
               <l>Will come by ready meanes vnto his end:</l>
               <l>But things miſcounſelled muſt needs miſwend.</l>
               <l>Thus therefore I adviſe vpon the caſe,</l>
               <l>That not to any certaine trade or place,</l>
               <l>Nor any man we ſhould our ſelues apply;</l>
               <l>For, why ſhould he that is at liberty</l>
               <l>Make himſelfe bond? Sith then we are free horne,</l>
               <l>Let vs all ſeruile baſe ſubjection ſcorne;</l>
               <l>And as we be ſonnes of the world ſo wide,</l>
               <l>Let vs our fathers heritage divide,</l>
               <l>And challenge to our ſelues our portions dew</l>
               <l>Of all the patrimony, which a few</l>
               <l>Now hold in hugger mugger in their hand,</l>
               <l>And all the reſt doe rob of good and land.</l>
               <l>For now a few haue all, and all haue nought,</l>
               <l>Yet all be brethren ylike dearely bought:</l>
               <l>There is no right in this partition,</l>
               <l>Ne was it ſo by inſtitution</l>
               <l>Ordained firſt, ne by the law of Nature,</l>
               <l>But that ſhe gaue like bleſſing to each creature</l>
               <l>As well of worldly liuelode as of life,</l>
               <l>That there might be no difference nor ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Nor ought call'd mine or thine: thrice happy then</l>
               <l>Was the condition of mortall men.</l>
               <l>That was the golden age of <hi>Saturne</hi> old,</l>
               <l>But this might better be the world of gold<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For without gold now nothing will be got.</l>
               <l>Therefore (if pleaſe you) this ſhall be our plot,</l>
               <l>We will not be of any occupation.</l>
               <l>Let ſuch vile vaſſalls borne to baſe vocation</l>
               <l>Drudge in the world, and for their liuing droyle</l>
               <l>Which haue no wit to liue withouten toyle.</l>
               <l>But we will walke about the world at pleaſure</l>
               <l>Like two free men, and make our eaſe a treaſure.</l>
               <l>Free men ſome beggers call; but they be free,</l>
               <l>And they which call them ſo more beggers bee<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For they doe ſwinke and ſweat to feed the other,</l>
               <l>Who liues like Lords of that which they doe gather,</l>
               <l>And yet doe neuer thanke them for the ſame,</l>
               <l>But as their due by nature do it claime.</l>
               <l>Such will we faſhion both our ſelues to be,</l>
               <l>Lords of the world, and ſo will wander free</l>
               <l>Where ſo vs liſteth, vncontroul'd of any<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hard is our hap, if we (emongſt ſo many)</l>
               <l>Light not on ſome that may our ſtate amend;</l>
               <l>Seldome but ſome good commeth ere the end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well ſeem'd the Ape to like this ordinance:</l>
               <l>Yet well conſidering of the circumſtance,</l>
               <l>As pauſing in great doubt a while he ſtaid,</l>
               <l>And afterwards with graue adviſement ſaid;</l>
               <l>I cannot my liefe brother like but well</l>
               <l>The purpoſe of the complot which ye tell:</l>
               <l>For well I wot (compar'd to all the reſt</l>
               <l>Of each degree) that Beggers life is beſt:</l>
               <l>And they that thinke themſelues the beſt of all,</l>
               <l>Oft-times to begging are content to fall.</l>
               <l>But this I wote withall, that we ſhall runne</l>
               <l>Into great danger, like to be vndone,</l>
               <l>Wildly to wander thus in the worlds eye,</l>
               <l>Without Paſport or good warrantie,</l>
               <l>For feare leaſt we like rogues ſhould be reputed,</l>
               <l>And for care-marked beaſts abroad be bruted:</l>
               <l>Therefore I read, that we our counſells call,</l>
               <l>How to preuent this miſchiefe ere it fall,</l>
               <l>And how we may with moſt ſecuritie,</l>
               <l>Beg amongſt thoſe that beggers doe defie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Right well, deare Goſſip, ye adviſed haue,</l>
               <l>(Said then the Foxe) but I this doubt will ſaue;</l>
               <l>For ere we farther paſſe, I will deuize</l>
               <l>A Paſport for vs both in fitteſt wize,</l>
               <l>And by the name of Souldier vs protect;</l>
               <l>That now is thought a ciuill begging ſect.</l>
               <l>Be you the Souldier, for you likeſt are</l>
               <l>For manly ſemblance, and ſmall skill in warre:</l>
               <l>I will but waite on you, and as occaſion</l>
               <l>Falls out, my ſelfe fit for the ſame will faſhion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Paſport ended, both they forward went,</l>
               <l>The Ape clad Souldier-like, fit for th' intent,</l>
               <l>In a blew iacket with a croſſe of red,</l>
               <l>And many ſlits, as if that he had ſhed</l>
               <l>Much bloud through many wounds therein receiued,</l>
               <l>Which had the vſe of his right arme bereaued;</l>
               <l>Vpon his head an old Scotch cap he wore,</l>
               <l>With a plume feather all to peeces tore<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His breeches were made after the new cut,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Al Portugeſe,</hi> looſe like an empty gut;</l>
               <l>And his hoſe broken high aboue the heeling,</l>
               <l>And his ſhooes beaten out with traueling.</l>
               <l>But neither ſword nor dagger he did beare,</l>
               <l>Seemes that no foes reuengement he did feare;</l>
               <l>In ſtead of them a handſome bat he held,</l>
               <l>On which he leaned, as one farre in eld.</l>
               <l>Shame light on him, that through ſo falſe illuſion,</l>
               <l>Doth turne the name of Souldiers to abuſion,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:26504:4"/> And that which is the nobleſt
myſterie,</l>
               <l>Brings to reproach and common infamie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long they thus trauailed, yet neuer met</l>
               <l>Adventures, which might them a working ſet:</l>
               <l>Yet many wayes they ſought, and many tryed;</l>
               <l>Yet for their purpoſes none fit eſpyed.</l>
               <l>At laſt, they chaunc't to meete vpon the way,</l>
               <l>A ſimple husbandman in garments gray.</l>
               <l>Yet though his veſture were but meane and bace,</l>
               <l>A good yeoman he was of honeſt place.</l>
               <l>And more for thrift did care then for gay clothing:</l>
               <l>Gay without good, is good harts greateſt loathing.</l>
               <l>The Foxe him ſpying, bad the Ape him dight</l>
               <l>To play his part, for loe he was in ſight</l>
               <l>That (if he he err'd not) ſhould them entertaine,</l>
               <l>And yeeld them timely profit for their paine.</l>
               <l>Eftſoones the Ape himſelfe gan to vpreare,</l>
               <l>And on his ſhoulders high his bat to beare,</l>
               <l>As if good ſeruice he were fit to doe;</l>
               <l>But little thrift for him he did it to:</l>
               <l>And ſtoutly forward he his ſteps did ſtraine,</l>
               <l>That like a handſome ſwaine it him became.</l>
               <l>When-as they night approached, that good man</l>
               <l>Seeing them wandring looſely, firſt began</l>
               <l>T' enquire of cuſtome, what and whence they were?</l>
               <l>To whom the Ape, I am a ſouldiere,</l>
               <l>That late in warres haue ſpent my deareſt bloud,</l>
               <l>And in long ſeruice loſt both limbs and good,</l>
               <l>And now conſtrain'd that trade to ouer-giue,</l>
               <l>I driuen am to ſeeke ſome meanes to liue:</l>
               <l>Which might it you in pitty pleaſe t' afford,</l>
               <l>I would be ready both in deed and word,</l>
               <l>To doe you faithfull ſeruice all my daies.</l>
               <l>This yron world (that ſame he weeping ſaies)</l>
               <l>Brings downe the ſtouteſt harts to loweſt ſtate:</l>
               <l>For miſery doth braueſt mindes abate,</l>
               <l>And makes them ſeeke for that they wont to ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Of fortune and of hope at once for lorne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The honeſt man, that heard him thus complaine,</l>
               <l>Was grieu'd, as he had felt part of his paine;</l>
               <l>And well diſpos'd, him ſome reliefe to ſhowe,</l>
               <l>Askt if in husbandry he ought did knowe,</l>
               <l>To plough, to plant, to reape, to rake, to ſowe,</l>
               <l>To hedge, to ditch, to threſh, to thatch, to mowe;</l>
               <l>Or to what labour elſe he was prepar'd?</l>
               <l>For husbands life is labourous and hard.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When-as the Ape him heard ſo much to talke</l>
               <l>Of labour, that did from his liking balke,</l>
               <l>He would haue ſlipt the coller handſomely</l>
               <l>And to him ſaid; Good Sir, full glad am I,</l>
               <l>To take what paines may any liuing wight:</l>
               <l>But my late maimed limbs lack wonted might</l>
               <l>To doe their kindly ſeruices, as needeth:</l>
               <l>Scarce this right hand the mouth with diet feedeth,</l>
               <l>So that it may no painfull worke endure,</l>
               <l>Ne to ſtrong labour can it ſelfe enure.</l>
               <l>But if that any other place you haue,</l>
               <l>Which asks ſmall paines, but thriftineſſe to ſaue,</l>
               <l>Or care to ouer-looke, or truſt to gather,</l>
               <l>Ye may me truſt as your owne ghoſtly father.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With that the husbandman gan him avize,</l>
               <l>That it for him was fitteſt exerciſe</l>
               <l>Cattell to keepe, or ground to ouer-ſee;</l>
               <l>And asked him if he could willing be</l>
               <l>To keepe his ſheepe, or to attend his ſwine,</l>
               <l>Or watch his mares, or take his charge of kine?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gladly (ſaid he) what euer ſuch like paine</l>
               <l>Ye put on me, I will the ſame ſuſtaine:</l>
               <l>But gladlieſt I of your fleecie ſheepe</l>
               <l>(Might it you pleaſe) would take on me the keepe.</l>
               <l>For ere that vnto armes I me betooke,</l>
               <l>Vnto my Fathers ſheepe I vs'd to looke,</l>
               <l>That yet the skill thereof I haue not loſt:</l>
               <l>There-to right well this Curdogg by my coſte</l>
               <l>(Meaning the Foxe) will ſerue, my ſheepe to gather,</l>
               <l>And driue to follow after their Belwether.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Husbandman was meanely well content,</l>
               <l>Triall to make of his endeuourment,</l>
               <l>And home him leading, lent to him the charge</l>
               <l>Of all his flock, with liberty full large,</l>
               <l>Giuing account of th' annuall increaſe.</l>
               <l>Both of their Lambs, and of their woolly fleece.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus is this Ape become a ſhepheard ſwaine,</l>
               <l>And the falſe Foxe, his dog (God giue them paine)</l>
               <l>For, ere the yeere haue halfe his courſe out-run,</l>
               <l>And doe returne from whence it firſt begun,</l>
               <l>They ſhall him make an ill account of thrift.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, when-as Time flying with wings ſwift,</l>
               <l>Expired had the terme, that theſe two iavels</l>
               <l>Should render vp a reckning of their trauels</l>
               <l>Vnto their maſter, which it of them ſought,</l>
               <l>Exceedingly they troubled were in thought,</l>
               <l>Ne wiſt what anſwer vnto him to frame,</l>
               <l>Ne how to ſcape great puniſhment, or ſhame,</l>
               <l>For their falſe treaſon and vile theeuery.</l>
               <l>For, not a lambe of all their flocks ſupply</l>
               <l>Had they to ſhew: but euer as they bred,</l>
               <l>They ſlew them, and vpon their fleſhes fed:</l>
               <l>For that diſguiſed dog lov'd blood to ſpill,</l>
               <l>And drew the wicked ſhepheard to his will.</l>
               <l>So twixt them both they not a lambkin left,</l>
               <l>And when lambes fayl'd, the old ſheepes liues they reſt;</l>
               <l>That how t' acquite themſelues vnto their Lord,</l>
               <l>They were in doubt, and flatly ſet abord.</l>
               <l>The Foxe then counſell'd th' Ape, for to require</l>
               <l>Reſpite till morrow, t' anſwer his deſire:</l>
               <l>For times delay new hope of helpe ſtill breedes.</l>
               <l>The goodman granted, doubting nought their deeds,</l>
               <l>And bad next day that all ſhould ready be.</l>
               <l>But they more ſubtill meaning had then he:</l>
               <l>For the next morrowes meed they cloſely ment,</l>
               <l>For feare of after claps for to prevent.</l>
               <l>And that ſame euening, when all ſhrowded were</l>
               <l>In careleſſe ſleepe, they without care or feare,</l>
               <l>Cruelly fell vpon their flock in folde,</l>
               <l>And of them ſlew at pleaſure what they wolde:</l>
               <l>Of which, when as they feaſted had their fill,</l>
               <l>For a full complement of all their ill,</l>
               <l>They ſtole away, and tooke their haſtie flight,</l>
               <l>Carried in clowdes of all-concealing night.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:26504:5"/> So was the husbandman left to his
loſſe,</l>
               <l>And they vnto their fortunes change to toſſe.</l>
               <l>After which ſort they wandered long while,</l>
               <l>Abuſing many through their cloked guile;</l>
               <l>That at the laſt they gan to be deſcried</l>
               <l>Of euery one, and all their ſleights eſpied.</l>
               <l>So as their begging now them failed quite;</l>
               <l>For none would giue, but all men would them wyte:</l>
               <l>Yet would they take no paines to get their liuing,</l>
               <l>But ſeeke ſome other way to gaine by giuing,</l>
               <l>Much like to begging, but much better named;</l>
               <l>For many beg, which are thereof aſhamed.</l>
               <l>And now the Foxe had gotten him a gowne,</l>
               <l>And th' Aape a caſſocke ſide-long hanging downe;</l>
               <l>For they their occupation meant to change,</l>
               <l>And now in other ſtate abroad to range:</l>
               <l>For, ſince their ſouldiers Pas no better ſpedd,</l>
               <l>They forg'd another, as for Clerks, booke-redd.</l>
               <l>Who paſſing forth, as their aduentures fell,</l>
               <l>Through many haps, which needs not here to tell;</l>
               <l>At length, chanc't with a formall Prieſt to meete,</l>
               <l>Whom they in ciuill manner firſt did greet,</l>
               <l>And after askt an almes for Gods deare loue.</l>
               <l>The man ſtraight-way his choler vp did moue,</l>
               <l>And with reproachfull tearmes gan them reuile,</l>
               <l>For following that trade ſo baſe and vile;</l>
               <l>And askt what Licence, or what Pas they had.</l>
               <l>Ah (ſaid the Ape, as ſighing wondrous ſad)</l>
               <l>It's an hard caſe, when men of good deſeruing</l>
               <l>Muſt either driuen be perforce to ſteruing,</l>
               <l>Or asked for their Pas by euery ſquib,</l>
               <l>That liſt at will them to reuile or ſnib:</l>
               <l>And yet (God wote) ſmall oddes I often ſee</l>
               <l>Twixt them that aske, and them that asked bee.</l>
               <l>Natheleſſe, becauſe you ſhall not vs miſdeeme,</l>
               <l>But that we are as honeſt as we ſeeme,</l>
               <l>Yee ſhall our Paſport at your pleaſure ſee,</l>
               <l>And then ye will (I hope) well mooued bee.</l>
               <l>Which when the Prieſt beheld, he view'd it neere,</l>
               <l>As if therein ſome Text he ſtudying were;</l>
               <l>But little elſe (God wote) could thereof skill:</l>
               <l>For, tead he could not Euidence, nor Will,</l>
               <l>Ne tell a written word, ne write a letter,</l>
               <l>Ne make one tittle worſe, ne make one better:</l>
               <l>Of ſuch deepe learning little had he neede,</l>
               <l>Ne yet of Latine, ne of Greeke, that breede</l>
               <l>Doubts mongſt Diuines, and difference of Texts,</l>
               <l>From whence ariſe diuerſitie of Sects,</l>
               <l>And hatefull hereſies of God abhorr'd:</l>
               <l>But this good Sir did follow the plaine Word,</l>
               <l>Ne medled with their controuerſies vaine,</l>
               <l>All his care was, his ſeruice well to ſaine,</l>
               <l>And to read Homelies on holidayes,</l>
               <l>When that was done, he might attend his playes;</l>
               <l>An eaſie life, and fit high God to pleaſe.</l>
               <l>He, hauing ouer-lookt their Pas at eaſe,</l>
               <l>Gan at the length them to rebuke againe,</l>
               <l>That no good trade of life did entertaine,</l>
               <l>But loſt their time in wandring looſe abroad,</l>
               <l>Seeing the world, in which they bootleſſe boad,</l>
               <l>Had waies enow for all therein to liue;</l>
               <l>Such grace did God vnto his creatures giue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Said then the Fox; Who hath the world not tride,</l>
               <l>From the right way full eath may wander wide.</l>
               <l>We are but Nouices, new come abroad,</l>
               <l>We haue not yet the tract of any troad,</l>
               <l>Nor on vs taken any ſtate of life,</l>
               <l>But ready are of any to make priefe.</l>
               <l>Therefore, might pleaſe you, which the world haue proued,</l>
               <l>Vs to aduiſe, which forth but lately moued,</l>
               <l>Of ſome good courſe, that we might vndertake<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ye ſhall for euer vs your bondmen make.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Prieſt gan wexe halfe proud to be ſo praide,</l>
               <l>And thereby willing to affoord them ayde;</l>
               <l>It ſeemes (ſaid he) right well that ye be Clerks,</l>
               <l>Both by your witty words, and by your werkes.</l>
               <l>Is not that name enough to make a liuing</l>
               <l>To him that hath a whit of Natures giuing?</l>
               <l>How many honeſt men ſee yee arize</l>
               <l>Daily thereby, and growe to goodly prize?</l>
               <l>To Deanes, to Archdeacons, to Commiſſaries,</l>
               <l>To Lords, to Principalls, to Prebendaries;</l>
               <l>All iolly Prelates, worthy rule to beare,</l>
               <l>Who euer them envie: yet ſpight bites neare.</l>
               <l>Why ſhould ye doubt then, but that ye likewiſe</l>
               <l>Might vnto ſome of thoſe in time ariſe?</l>
               <l>In the meane time to liue in good eſtate,</l>
               <l>Louing that loue, and hating thoſe that hate;</l>
               <l>Beeing ſome honeſt Curate, or ſome Vicker,</l>
               <l>Content with little in condition ſicker.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah! but (ſaith th' Ape) the charge is wondrous great,</l>
               <l>To feede mens ſoules, and hath an heauy threat.</l>
               <l>To feed mens ſoules (quoth he) is not in man:</l>
               <l>For, they muſt feed themſelues, doe what we can.</l>
               <l>We are but charg'd to lay the meat before:</l>
               <l>Eate they that liſt, we need to doe no more.</l>
               <l>But God it is that feeds them with his grace,</l>
               <l>The bread of life pour'd downe from heauenly place.</l>
               <l>Therefore ſaid he, that with the budding rod</l>
               <l>Did rule the Iewes, <hi>All ſhall be taught of God.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That ſame hath Ieſus Chriſt now to him raught,</l>
               <l>By whom the flocks is rightly fed and taught<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He is the Shepheard, and the Prieſt is he;</l>
               <l>We but his Shepheard ſwaines ordain'd to bee.</l>
               <l>Therefore heere-with doe not your ſelfe diſmay;</l>
               <l>Ne is the paines ſo great, but beare ye may;</l>
               <l>For not ſo great as it was wont of yore,</l>
               <l>It's now adayes, ne halfe ſo ſtraight and ſore.</l>
               <l>They whylome vſed duly euery day</l>
               <l>Their ſeruice and their holy things to ſay,</l>
               <l>At noone and euen, beſides their Anthemes ſweet,</l>
               <l>Their peny Maſſes, and their Complynes meet,</l>
               <l>Their Diriges, their Trentals, and their ſhrifts,</l>
               <l>Their memories, their ſingings, and their gifts.</l>
               <l>Now all theſe needleſſe workes, are laid away;</l>
               <l>Now once a weeke vpon the Sabbath day,</l>
               <l>It is enough to doe our ſmall deuotion,</l>
               <l>And then to follow any merry motion.</l>
               <l>Ne are we tyde to faſt, but when we liſt,</l>
               <l>Ne to weare garments baſe of wollen twiſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:26504:5"/> But with the fineſt ſilks vs to aray,</l>
               <l>That before God we may appeare more gay,</l>
               <l>Reſembling <hi>Aarons</hi> glory in his place:</l>
               <l>For farre vnfit it is, that perſons bace</l>
               <l>Should with vile cloathes approach Gods maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Whom no vncleannes may approchen nie:</l>
               <l>Or that all men which any maſter ſerue,</l>
               <l>Good garments for their ſeruice ſhould deſerue;</l>
               <l>But he that ſerues the Lord of hoaſts moſt high,</l>
               <l>And that in higheſt place, t' approach him nigh,</l>
               <l>And all the peoples prayers to preſent</l>
               <l>Before his throne, as on ambaſſage ſent</l>
               <l>Both to and fro, ſhould not deſerue to weare</l>
               <l>A garment better, than of wooll or haire.</l>
               <l>Beſide, we may haue lying by our ſides</l>
               <l>Our louely Laſſes, or bright ſhining Brides:</l>
               <l>We be not tyde to wilfull chaſtitie,</l>
               <l>But haue the Goſpell of free libertie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By that he ended had his ghoſtly ſermon,</l>
               <l>The Foxe was well induc'd to be a Parſon;</l>
               <l>And of the Prieſt eftſoones gan to enquire,</l>
               <l>How to a Benefice he might aſpire.</l>
               <l>Marie there (ſaid the Prieſt) is art indeede.</l>
               <l>Much good deepe learning one thereout may reed,</l>
               <l>For, that the ground-worke is, and end of all,</l>
               <l>How to obtaine a Beneficiall.</l>
               <l>Firſt therefore, when ye haue in handſome wiſe</l>
               <l>Your ſelues attired, as you can deuiſe,</l>
               <l>Then to ſome Noble man your ſelfe apply,</l>
               <l>Or other great one in the worldes eye,</l>
               <l>That hath a zealous diſpoſition</l>
               <l>To God, and ſo to his religion:</l>
               <l>There muſt thou faſhion eke a godly zeale,</l>
               <l>Such as no capers may contrayre reueale<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, each thing fained ought more warie be.</l>
               <l>There muſt thou walke in ſober grauitee,</l>
               <l>And ſeeme as Saint-like as Saint <hi>Radegund:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Faſt much, pray oft, looke lowely on the ground,</l>
               <l>And vnto euery one doe curteſie meeke:</l>
               <l>Theſe lookes (nought ſaying) doe a Benefice ſeeke,</l>
               <l>And be thou ſure one not to lack ere long.</l>
               <l>But if thee liſt vnto the Court to throng,</l>
               <l>And there to hunt after the hoped pray,</l>
               <l>Then muſt thou thee diſpoſe another way:</l>
               <l>For there thou needs muſt learne, to laugh, to lie,</l>
               <l>To face, to forge, to ſcoffe, to company,</l>
               <l>To crouche, to pleaſe, to be a beetle ſtock</l>
               <l>Of thy great Maſters will, to ſcorne, or mock:</l>
               <l>So maiſt thou chance mock out a benefice,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe thou canſt one coniure by deuice,</l>
               <l>Or caſt a figure for a Biſhoprick:</l>
               <l>And if one could, it were but a ſchoole-trick.</l>
               <l>Theſe be the waies, by which without reward</l>
               <l>Liuings in Court be gotten, though full hard.</l>
               <l>For nothing there is done without a fee<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Courtier needs muſt recompenced bee</l>
               <l>With a Beneuolence, or haue in gage</l>
               <l>The <hi>Primilias</hi> of your Parſonage:</l>
               <l>Scarce can a Biſhoprick for pas them by,</l>
               <l>But that it muſt be gelt in priuitie.</l>
               <l>Doe not thou therefore ſeeke a liuing there,</l>
               <l>But of more priuate perſons ſeeke elſwhere,</l>
               <l>Where-as thou maiſt compound a better pennie,</l>
               <l>Ne let thy learning queſtion'd be of any.</l>
               <l>For ſome good Gentleman that hath the right</l>
               <l>Vnto his Church for to preſent a wight,</l>
               <l>Will cope with thee in reaſonable wiſe;</l>
               <l>That if the liuing yeerely doe ariſe</l>
               <l>To fortie pound, that then his yongeſt ſonne</l>
               <l>Shall twenty haue, and twenty thou haſt wonne:</l>
               <l>Thou haſt it wonne, for it is of franke gift,</l>
               <l>And he will care for all the reſt to ſhift;</l>
               <l>Both, that the Biſhop may admit of thee,</l>
               <l>And that therein thou maiſt maintaine I bee.</l>
               <l>This is the way for one that is vnlearn'd</l>
               <l>Liuing to get, and not to be diſcern'd.</l>
               <l>But they that are great Clerks, haue neerer wayes,</l>
               <l>For learning ſake to liuing them to raiſe:</l>
               <l>Yet many eke of them (God wote) are driuen,</l>
               <l>T' accept a Benefice in peeces riuen.</l>
               <l>How ſai'ſt thou (friend) haue I not well diſcourſt</l>
               <l>Vpon this Common place (though plaine, not wourſt)?</l>
               <l>Better a ſhort tale, then a bad long ſhriuing.</l>
               <l>Needes any more to learne to get a liuing?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſure and by my hallidome (quoth he)</l>
               <l>Yea great maſter are in your degree<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Great thanks, I yeeld you for your diſcipline,</l>
               <l>And doe not doubt, but duly to encline</l>
               <l>My wits thereto, as ye ſhall ſhortly heare.</l>
               <l>The Preiſt him wiſht good ſpeed, and well to fare.</l>
               <l>So parted they, as eithers way them led.</l>
               <l>But th' Ape and Foxe ere long ſo well them ſped,</l>
               <l>Through the Preiſts wholſome counſell lately tought,</l>
               <l>And through their owne faire handling wiſely wrought,</l>
               <l>That they a Benefice twixt them obtained;</l>
               <l>And crafty Reynold was a Preiſt ordained;</l>
               <l>And th' Ape his Pariſh Clarke procur'd to bee.</l>
               <l>Then made they reuell route and goodly glee.</l>
               <l>But ere long time had paſſed, they ſo ill</l>
               <l>Did order their affaires, that th' euill will</l>
               <l>Of all their Pariſhners they had conſtrain'd;</l>
               <l>Who to the Ordinarie of them complain'd,</l>
               <l>How fouly they their offices abus'd,</l>
               <l>And them of crimes and hereſies accus'd;</l>
               <l>That Purſiuants he often for them ſent:</l>
               <l>But they neglecting his commaundement</l>
               <l>So long perſiſted obſtinate and bold,</l>
               <l>Till at the length he publiſhed to hold</l>
               <l>A Viſitation, and them cyted thither:</l>
               <l>Then was high time their wits about to gather;</l>
               <l>What did they then, but made a compoſition</l>
               <l>With their next neighbour Prieſt for light condition,</l>
               <l>To whom their liuing they reſigned quight</l>
               <l>For a few pence, and ran away by night.</l>
               <l>So paſſing through the Countrey in diſguize,</l>
               <l>They fled far off, where none might them ſurprize,</l>
               <l>And after that long ſtraied heere and there,</l>
               <l>Through euery field and forreſt farre and neere;</l>
               <l>Yet neuer found occaſion for their tourne,</l>
               <l>But almoſt ſteru'd, did much lament and mourne.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:26504:6"/> At laſt, they chaunc't to meet vpon the
way</l>
               <l>The Mule, all deckt in goodly rich aray,</l>
               <l>With bells and boſſes, that full lowdly rung,</l>
               <l>And coſtly trappings, that to ground downe hung.</l>
               <l>Lowly they him ſaluted in meeke wiſe;</l>
               <l>But he through pride and fatnes gan deſpiſe</l>
               <l>Their meanneſſe; ſcarce vouchſafe them to requite.</l>
               <l>Whereat the Foxe deepe groning in his ſprite,</l>
               <l>Said, Ah! ſir Mule, now bleſſed be the day,</l>
               <l>That I ſee you ſo goodly and ſo gay</l>
               <l>In your attyres, and eke your ſilken hyde</l>
               <l>Fill'd with round fleſh, that euery bone doth hide.</l>
               <l>Seemes that in fruitfull paſtures you doe liue,</l>
               <l>Or Fortune doth you ſecret fauour giue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fooliſh Foxe (ſaid the Mule) thy wretched need</l>
               <l>Praiſeth the thing that doth thy ſorrow breed.</l>
               <l>For well I weene, thou canſt not but enuie</l>
               <l>My wealth, compar'd to thine owne miſery,</l>
               <l>That art ſo leane and meagre waxen late,</l>
               <l>That ſcarce thy legs vphold thy feeble gate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ay me <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſaid then the Foxe) whom euill hap</l>
               <l>Vnworthy in ſuch wretchednes doth wrap,</l>
               <l>And make the ſcorne of other beaſts to be<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But read (faire Sir, of grace) from whence come yee?</l>
               <l>Or what of tydings you abroad doe heare?</l>
               <l>Newes may perhaps ſome good vnweeting beare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>From royall Court I lately came (ſaid he)</l>
               <l>Where all the brauerie that eye may ſee,</l>
               <l>And all the happineſſe that heart deſire,</l>
               <l>Is to be found; he nothing can admire,</l>
               <l>That hath not ſeene that heauens portracture:</l>
               <l>But tydings there is none I you aſſure,</l>
               <l>Saue that which common is, and knowne to all,</l>
               <l>That Courtiers as the tyde doe riſe and fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But, tell vs (ſaid the Ape) we doe you pray,</l>
               <l>Who now in Court doth beare the greateſt ſway.</l>
               <l>That if ſuch fortune doe to vs befall,</l>
               <l>We may ſeeke fauour of the beſt of all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Marie (ſaid he) the higheſt now in grace,</l>
               <l>Be the wilde beaſts, that ſwifteſt are in chaſe;</l>
               <l>For in their ſpeedie courſe and nimble flight</l>
               <l>The Lion now doth take the moſt delight:</l>
               <l>But chiefely, ioyes on foote them to behold,</l>
               <l>Enchaſte with chaine and circulet of gold:</l>
               <l>So wilde a beaſt ſo tame ytaught to be,</l>
               <l>And buxonie to his bands is ioy to ſee.</l>
               <l>So well his golden Circlet him beſeemeth:</l>
               <l>But his late chaine his Liege vnmeet eſteemeth;</l>
               <l>For ſo braue beaſts he loueth beſt to ſee</l>
               <l>In the wilde forreſt raunging freſh and free.</l>
               <l>Therefore if fortune thee in Court to liue,</l>
               <l>In caſe thou euer there wilt hope to thriue,</l>
               <l>To ſome of theſe thou muſt thy ſelfe apply<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Elſe, as a thiſtle-downe in th' ayre doth flie,</l>
               <l>So, vainely ſhalt thou to and fro be toſt,</l>
               <l>And loſe thy labour and thy fruitleſſe coſt.</l>
               <l>And yet full few that follow them I ſee,</l>
               <l>For vertues bare regard aduaunced be,</l>
               <l>But either for ſome gainefull benefit,</l>
               <l>Or that they may for their owne turnes be ſit.</l>
               <l>Nath'leſſe, perhaps, ye things may handle ſo,</l>
               <l>That ye may better thriue then thouſands mo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But (ſaid the Ape) how ſhall we firſt come in,</l>
               <l>That after we may fauour ſeeke to win?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How elſe (ſaid he) but with a good bold face,</l>
               <l>And with big words, and with a ſtately pace,</l>
               <l>That men may thinke of you in generall,</l>
               <l>That to be in you which is not at all:</l>
               <l>For, not by that which is, the world now deemeth</l>
               <l>(As it was wont) but by that ſame it ſeemeth.</l>
               <l>Ne doe I doubt but that ye well can faſhion</l>
               <l>Your ſelues there-to, according to occaſion:</l>
               <l>So fare you well, good Courtiers may ye bee;</l>
               <l>So proudly neighing, from them parted he.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then gan this craftie couple to deuize,</l>
               <l>How for the Court themſelues they might aguize:</l>
               <l>For thither they themſelues meant to addreſſe,</l>
               <l>In hope to finde their happier ſucceſſe;</l>
               <l>So well they ſhifted, that the Ape anon</l>
               <l>Himſelfe had clothed like a Gentleman,</l>
               <l>And the ſlie Fox, as like to be his groome,</l>
               <l>That to the Court in ſeemely ſort they come.</l>
               <l>Where the fond Ape himſelfe vprearing hy</l>
               <l>Vpon his tiptoes, ſtalketh ſtately by,</l>
               <l>As if he were ſome great <hi>Magnifice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And boldly doth amongſt the boldeſt go.</l>
               <l>And his man Reynold with fine counterfeſaunce</l>
               <l>Supports his credite and his countenaunce.</l>
               <l>Then gan the Courtiers gaze on euery ſide,</l>
               <l>And ſtare on him, with big lookes baſen wide,</l>
               <l>Wondring what miſter wight he was, and whence:</l>
               <l>For he was clad in ſtrange accouſtrements,</l>
               <l>Faſhion'd with huient deuiſes neuer ſeene</l>
               <l>In Court before, yet there all faſhions beene:</l>
               <l>Yet he them in new fangleneſſe did paſſe:</l>
               <l>But his behauiour altogether was</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alla Turcheſca,</hi> much the more admyr'd,</l>
               <l>And his lookes loftie, as if he aſpyr'd</l>
               <l>To dignitie, and ſdeign'd the lowe degree;</l>
               <l>That all which did ſuch ſtrangeneſſe in him ſee,</l>
               <l>By ſecret meanes gan of his ſtate enquire,</l>
               <l>And priuily his ſeruant thereto hire:</l>
               <l>Who, throughly arm'd againſt ſuch couerture,</l>
               <l>Reported vnto all, that he was ſure</l>
               <l>A noble Gentleman of his regard,</l>
               <l>Which, through the world had with long trauell far'd,</l>
               <l>And ſeene the manners of all beaſts on ground;</l>
               <l>Now heere arriu'd, to ſee if like he found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus did the Ape at firſt him credit gaine,</l>
               <l>Which afterwards he wiſely did maintaine</l>
               <l>With gallant ſhowe, and daily more augment</l>
               <l>Through his fine feats and Courtly complement;</l>
               <l>For he could play, and daunce, and vaute, and ſpring,</l>
               <l>And all that elſe pertaines to reuelling,</l>
               <l>Onely through kindly aptnes of his ioynts.</l>
               <l>Beſides, he could doe many other poynts,</l>
               <l>The which in Court him ſerued to good ſtead:</l>
               <l>For, he mongſt Ladies could their fortunes read</l>
               <l>Out of their hands, and merie leaſings tell,</l>
               <l>And iuggle finely, that became him well:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:26504:6"/> But he ſo light was at legier-demaine,</l>
               <l>That what he toucht, came not to light againe;</l>
               <l>Yet would he laugh it out, and proudly looke,</l>
               <l>And tell them, that they greatly him miſtooke.</l>
               <l>So would he ſcoffe them out with mockerie,</l>
               <l>For he therein had great felicitie;</l>
               <l>And with ſharp quips ioy'd others to deface,</l>
               <l>Thinking that their diſgracing did him grace:</l>
               <l>So whilſt that other like vaine wits he pleaſed,</l>
               <l>And made to laugh, his heart was greatly eaſed.</l>
               <l>But the right gentle mind would bite his lip,</l>
               <l>To heare the lauell ſo good men to nip:</l>
               <l>For though the vulgar yeeld an open eare,</l>
               <l>And common Courtiers loue to gybe and fleare</l>
               <l>At euery thing, which they heare ſpoken ill,</l>
               <l>And the beſt ſpeeches with ill meaning ſpill;</l>
               <l>Yet the braue Courtier, in whoſe beautious thought</l>
               <l>Regard of honour harbours more than ought,</l>
               <l>Doth loath ſuch baſe condition, to backbite</l>
               <l>Anies good name for envie or deſpite:</l>
               <l>He ſtands on tearmes of honourable mind,</l>
               <l>Ne will be carried with the common wind</l>
               <l>Of Courts inconſtant mutabilitie,</l>
               <l>Ne after euery tattling fable flie;</l>
               <l>But heares, and ſees the follies of the reſt,</l>
               <l>And thereof gathers for himſelfe the beſt:</l>
               <l>He will not creepe, nor crouch with fained face,</l>
               <l>But walks vpright with comely ſtedfaſt pace,</l>
               <l>And vnto all doth yeeld due curtefie;</l>
               <l>But not with kiſſed hand belowe the knee,</l>
               <l>As that fame Apiſh crue is wont to doe:</l>
               <l>For he diſdaines himſelfe t' embaſe there-to.</l>
               <l>He hates foule leaſings, and vile flatterie,</l>
               <l>Two fithy blots in noble Gentrie;</l>
               <l>And lothefull idlenes he doth deteſt,</l>
               <l>The canker-worme of euery gentle breſt:</l>
               <l>The which to baniſh with faire excerciſe</l>
               <l>Of knightly feates, he daily doth deuiſe:</l>
               <l>Now menaging the mouthes of ſtubborne ſteedes:</l>
               <l>Now practiſing the proofe of warlike deedes,</l>
               <l>Now his bright armes aſſaying, now his ſpeare,</l>
               <l>Now the nigh-aymed ring away to beare;</l>
               <l>At other times he caſts to ſew the chace</l>
               <l>Of ſwift wilde beaſts, or runne on foote a race,</l>
               <l>Ten large his breath (large breath in armes moſt needful)</l>
               <l>Or elſe by wreſtling to wex ſtrong and heedfull,</l>
               <l>Or his ſtiffe armes to ſtretch with Eughen bowe,</l>
               <l>And manly legs, ſtill paſſing to and fro,</l>
               <l>Without a gowned beaſt him faſt beſide;</l>
               <l>A vaine enſample of rhe <hi>Perfian</hi> pride,</l>
               <l>Who after he had wonne th' <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> foe,</l>
               <l>Did euer after ſcorne on foote to goe.</l>
               <l>Thus when this Courtly Gentleman with toyle</l>
               <l>Himſefe hath wearied, he doth recoyle</l>
               <l>Vnto his reſt, and there with ſweet delight</l>
               <l>Of Muſicks skill reuiues his toyled ſpright;</l>
               <l>Or elſe with Loues, and Ladies gentle ſports,</l>
               <l>The ioy of youth, himſelfe he recomforts:</l>
               <l>Or laſtly, when the body liſt to pauſe,</l>
               <l>His minde vnto the Muſes he with-drawes;</l>
               <l>Sweet Lady Muſes, Ladies of delight,</l>
               <l>Delights of life, and ornaments of light:</l>
               <l>With whom he cloſe confers with wiſe diſcourſe,</l>
               <l>Of Natures workes, of heauens continuall courſe,</l>
               <l>Of forraine lands, of people different,</l>
               <l>Of kingdoms change, of diuers gouernment,</l>
               <l>Of dreadfull battailes, of renowned Knights;</l>
               <l>With which he kindleth his ambitious ſprights</l>
               <l>To like deſire and praiſe of noble fame,</l>
               <l>The onely vp-ſhot where-to he doth aime:</l>
               <l>For all his mind on honour fixed is,</l>
               <l>To which he leuels all his purpoſes,</l>
               <l>And in his Princes ſeruice ſpends his daies,</l>
               <l>Not ſo much for to gaine, or for to raiſe</l>
               <l>Himſelfe to high degree; as for his grace,</l>
               <l>And in his liking to winne worthy place,</l>
               <l>Through due deſerts and comely carriage,</l>
               <l>In what-ſo pleaſe employ his perſonage,</l>
               <l>That may be matter meet to gaine him praiſe;</l>
               <l>For he is fit to vſe in all aſſayes,</l>
               <l>Whether for Armes and warlike amenaunce,</l>
               <l>Or elſe for wiſe and ciuill gouernaunce.</l>
               <l>For he is practiz'd well in policie,</l>
               <l>And there-to doth his courting moſt apply:</l>
               <l>To learne the enterdeale of Princes ſtrange,</l>
               <l>To marke th' intent of Counſells, and the change</l>
               <l>Of States, and eke of priuate men ſome-while,</l>
               <l>Supplanted by fine falſhood and faire guile;</l>
               <l>Of all the which he gathereth what is fit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>T' enrich the ſtorehouſe of his powerfull wit,</l>
               <l>Which through wiſe ſpeeches, and graue conference</l>
               <l>He daily eekes, and brings to excellence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such is the rightfull Courtier in his kind:</l>
               <l>But vnto ſuch the Ape lent not his mind;</l>
               <l>Such were for him no fit companions,</l>
               <l>Such would deſcry his lewd conditions:</l>
               <l>But the young luſtie gallants he did choſe</l>
               <l>To follow, meet to whom he might diſcloſe</l>
               <l>His witleſſe pleaſance, and ill-pleaſing vaine.</l>
               <l>A thouſand wayes he them could entertaine,</l>
               <l>With all the thriftleſſe games that may be found,</l>
               <l>With mumming and with masking all around,</l>
               <l>With dice, with cards, with balliards far vnfit,</l>
               <l>With ſhuttle cocks, miſ-ſeming manly wit,</l>
               <l>With courtizans, and coſtly riotize,</l>
               <l>Whereof ſtill ſomewhat to his ſhare did rize:</l>
               <l>Ne, them to pleaſure, would he ſometimes ſcorne</l>
               <l>A Pandars coate (ſo baſely was he borne):</l>
               <l>There-to he could fine louing verſes frame,</l>
               <l>And play the Poet oft. But ah! for ſhame,</l>
               <l>Let not ſweet Poets praiſe, whoſe onely pride</l>
               <l>Is vertue to advaunce, and vice deride,</l>
               <l>Be with the worke of loſels wit defamed,</l>
               <l>Ne let ſuch verſes Poetry be named:</l>
               <l>Yet he the name on him would raſhly take,</l>
               <l>Maugre the ſacred Muſes, and it make</l>
               <l>A ſeruant to the vile affection</l>
               <l>Of ſuch, as he depended moſt vpon,</l>
               <l>And with the ſugry ſweet thereof allure</l>
               <l>Chaſte Ladies eares to fantaſies impure,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:26504:7"/> To ſuch delights the noble wits he led</l>
               <l>Which him relieu'd and their vaine humors fed</l>
               <l>With fruitleſſe follies, and vnſound delights.</l>
               <l>But if perhaps, into their noble ſprights</l>
               <l>Deſire of honour, or braue thought of armes</l>
               <l>Did euer creepe, then with his wicked charmes</l>
               <l>And ſtrong conceits he would it driue away,</l>
               <l>Ne ſuffer it to houſe there halfe a day.</l>
               <l>And when ſo loue of letters did inſpire</l>
               <l>Their gentle wits, and kindly wiſe deſire</l>
               <l>That chiefly doth each noble mind adorne,</l>
               <l>Then he would ſcoffe at learning, and eke ſcorne</l>
               <l>The Sectaries thereof, as people bace,</l>
               <l>And ſimple men, which neuer came in place</l>
               <l>Of worlds affaires, but in darke corners mewd,</l>
               <l>Muttred of matters, as their bookes them ſhewd,</l>
               <l>Ne other knowledge euer did attaine,</l>
               <l>But with their gownes their grauitie maintaine.</l>
               <l>From them he would his impudent lewd ſpeech</l>
               <l>Againſt Gods holy Miniſters oft reach,</l>
               <l>And mock Diuines and their profeſſion:</l>
               <l>What elſe then did he by progreſſion,</l>
               <l>But mock high God himſelfe, whom they profeſſe?</l>
               <l>But what car'd he for God or godlinſſe?</l>
               <l>All his care was himſelfe how to aduance,</l>
               <l>And to vphold his courtly countenance</l>
               <l>By all the cunning meanes he could deuiſe;</l>
               <l>Were it by honeſt waies, or otherwiſe,</l>
               <l>He made ſmall choice: yet ſure his honeſtie</l>
               <l>Got him ſmall gaines, but ſhameleſſe flattery,</l>
               <l>And filthy brocage, and vnſeemly ſhifts,</l>
               <l>And borow baſe, and ſome good Ladies gifts<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But the beſt helpe, which chiefely him ſuſtain'd,</l>
               <l>Was his man Reynolds purchaſe which he gain'd.</l>
               <l>For he was ſchool'd by kind in all the skill</l>
               <l>Of cloſe conueyance, and each practiſe ill</l>
               <l>Of cooſinage and cleanly knauerie,</l>
               <l>Which oft maintain'd his maſters brauery.</l>
               <l>Beſides, he vs'd another ſlippery ſlight,</l>
               <l>In taking on himſelfe in common ſight,</l>
               <l>Falſe perſonages, fit for euery ſted,</l>
               <l>With which he thouſands cleanly cooſined:</l>
               <l>Now like a Merchant, Merchants to deceaue,</l>
               <l>With whom his credite he did often leaue</l>
               <l>In gage, for his gay Maſters hopeleſſe dett,</l>
               <l>Now like a Lawyer, when he land would lett,</l>
               <l>Or ſell fee-ſimples in his Maſters name,</l>
               <l>Which he had neuer, nor ought like the ſame:</l>
               <l>Then would he be a Broker, and draw in</l>
               <l>Both wares and money, by exchange to win:</l>
               <l>Then would he ſeeme a Farmer, that would ſell,</l>
               <l>Bargaines of woods, which he did lately fell,</l>
               <l>Or corne, or cattle, or ſuch other ware,</l>
               <l>There-by to cooſin men not well aware;</l>
               <l>Of all the which there came a ſecret fee</l>
               <l>To th' Ape, that he his countenance might be.</l>
               <l>Beſides all this, he vs'd oft to beguile</l>
               <l>Poore ſuters, that in Court did haunt ſome
while<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For he would learne their buſines ſecretly,</l>
               <l>And then informe his Maſter haſtily,</l>
               <l>That he by meanes might caſt them to preuent,</l>
               <l>And beg the ſute the which the other ment.</l>
               <l>Or otherwiſe, falſe Reynold would abuſe</l>
               <l>The ſimple Suter, and wiſh him to chuſe</l>
               <l>His Maſter, beeing one of great regard</l>
               <l>In Court, to compaſſe any ſute not hard,</l>
               <l>In caſe his paines were recompenc't with reaſon:</l>
               <l>So would he worke the ſilly man by treaſon</l>
               <l>To buy his Maſters friuolous good will,</l>
               <l>That had not power to do him good or ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So pittifull a thing is Suters ſtate.</l>
               <l>Moſt miſerable man, whom wicked fate</l>
               <l>Hath brought to Court, to ſue for had-ywiſt,</l>
               <l>That few haue found, and many one hath miſt;</l>
               <l>Full little knoweſt thou that haſt not tride,</l>
               <l>What hell it is, in ſuing long to bide:</l>
               <l>To looſe good dayes that might be better ſpent;</l>
               <l>To waſte long nights in penſiue diſcontent:</l>
               <l>To ſpeed to day, to be put back to morrow;</l>
               <l>To feed on hope, to pine with feare and ſorrow;</l>
               <l>To haue thy Princes grace, yet want her Peeres;</l>
               <l>To haue thy asking, yet waite many yeeres;</l>
               <l>To fret thy ſoule with croſſes and with cares;</l>
               <l>To eate thy heart through comfortleſſe deſpaires;</l>
               <l>To fawne, to crouch, to wait, to ride, to ronne;</l>
               <l>To ſpend, to giue, to want, to be vndonne,</l>
               <l>Vnhappy wight, borne to diſaſtrous end,</l>
               <l>That doth his life in ſo long tendance ſpend.</l>
               <l>Who euer leaues ſweet home, where meane eſtate</l>
               <l>In ſafe aſſurance, without ſtrife or hate,</l>
               <l>Findes all things needfull for contentment meeke;</l>
               <l>And will to Court for ſhadowes vaine to ſeeke,</l>
               <l>Or hope to gaine, himſelfe a daw will try:</l>
               <l>That curſe God ſend vnto mine enemie.</l>
               <l>For none but ſuch as this bold Ape vnbieſt,</l>
               <l>Can euer thriue in that vnlucky queſt;</l>
               <l>Or ſuch as hath a Reynold to his man,</l>
               <l>That by his ſhifts his Maſter furniſh can.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But yet this Foxe could not ſo cloſely hide</l>
               <l>His crafty feates, but that they were deſcride</l>
               <l>At length, by ſuch as ſate in iuſtice ſeat,</l>
               <l>Who for the ſame him fouly did entreat;</l>
               <l>And hauing worthily him puniſhed.</l>
               <l>Out of the Court for euer baniſhed,</l>
               <l>And now the Ape wanting his huckſter man,</l>
               <l>That wont prouide his neceſſaries gan</l>
               <l>To grow into great lack, ne could vp holde</l>
               <l>His countenance in thoſe his garments olde;</l>
               <l>Ne new ones could he eaſily prouide,</l>
               <l>Though all men him vncaſed gan deride,</l>
               <l>Like as a Puppit placed in a play,</l>
               <l>Whoſe part once paſt, all men bid take away:</l>
               <l>So that he driuen was to great diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>And ſhortly brought to hopeleſſe wretchedneſſe.</l>
               <l>Then cloſely as he might, he caſt to leaue</l>
               <l>The Court, not asking any Pas or leaue;</l>
               <l>But ran away in his rentrags by night,</l>
               <l>Ne euer ſtayd in place, ne ſpake to wight,</l>
               <l>Till that the Foxe his copeſmate he had found,</l>
               <l>To whom complayning his vnhappy ſtound,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:26504:7"/> At laſt againe with him in trauell
ioynd,</l>
               <l>And with him far'd ſome better chance to finde.</l>
               <l>So in the world long time they wandered,</l>
               <l>And mickle want and hardneſſe ſuffered;</l>
               <l>That them repented much ſo fooliſhly</l>
               <l>To come ſo farre to ſeeke for miſery,</l>
               <l>And leaue the ſweetnes of contented home,</l>
               <l>Though eating hips, and drinking watry fome.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus as they them complained to and fro,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt through the foreſt rechleſſe they did goe,</l>
               <l>Lo where they ſpide, how in a gloomy glade,</l>
               <l>The Lion ſleeping lay in ſecret ſhade,</l>
               <l>His Crowne and Scepter lying him beſide,</l>
               <l>And hauing doft for heat his dreadfull hide:</l>
               <l>Which when they ſawe, the Ape was ſore afraid,</l>
               <l>And would haue fled with terror all diſmaide.</l>
               <l>But him the Foxe with hardy words did ſtay,</l>
               <l>And bad him put all cowardize away:</l>
               <l>For now was time (if euer they would hope)</l>
               <l>To ayme their counſels to the faireſt ſcope,</l>
               <l>And them for euer highly to aduance,</l>
               <l>In caſe the good which their owne happy chance</l>
               <l>Them freely offred, they would wiſely take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Scarce could the Ape yet ſpeake, ſo did he quake,</l>
               <l>Yet as he could, he askt how good might growe,</l>
               <l>Where nought but dread and death do ſeeme in ſhowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now (ſaid he) whiles the Lion ſleepeth ſound,</l>
               <l>May we his Crowne and Mace take from the ground,</l>
               <l>And eke his skinne, the terror of the wood,</l>
               <l>Where-with we may our ſelues (if we thinke good)</l>
               <l>Make Kings of beaſts, and Lords of foreſts all,</l>
               <l>Subiect vnto that power imperiall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah! but (ſaid the Ape) who is ſo bold a wretch,</l>
               <l>That dare his hardy hand to thoſe out-ſtretch;</l>
               <l>When as he knowes his meed, if he be ſpide,</l>
               <l>To be a thouſand deaths, and ſhame beſide?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Fond Ape (ſaid then the Foxe) into whoſe breſt</l>
               <l>Neuer crept thought of honour, nor braue geſt,</l>
               <l>Who will not venture life a King to be,</l>
               <l>And rather rule and raigne in ſoueraigne ſee,</l>
               <l>Than dwell in duſt inglorious and bace,</l>
               <l>Where none ſhall name the number of his place?</l>
               <l>One ioyous houre in blisfull happineſſe,</l>
               <l>I chuſe before a life of wretchednes.</l>
               <l>Be therefore counſelled herein by me,</l>
               <l>And ſhake off this vile-harted cowardree.</l>
               <l>If he awake, yet is not death the next,</l>
               <l>For we may coulor it with ſome pretext</l>
               <l>Of this, or that, that may excuſe the crime:</l>
               <l>Elſe we may flye; thou to a tree mayſt clime,</l>
               <l>And I creepe vnder ground; both from his reach:</l>
               <l>Therefore be rul'd to doe as I doe teach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Ape, that earſt did nought but chill and quake,</l>
               <l>Now gan ſome courage vnto him to take,</l>
               <l>And was content to attempt that enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>Tickled with glory and raſh couetiſe;</l>
               <l>But firſt gan queſtion whether ſhould aſſay</l>
               <l>Thoſe royall ornaments to ſteale away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mary that ſhall your ſelfe (quoth he thereto)</l>
               <l>For ye be fine and nimble it to do;</l>
               <l>Of all the beaſts which in the foreſts be,</l>
               <l>Is not a fitter for this turne than yee<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Therefore mine owne deare brother take good heart,</l>
               <l>And euer thinke a kingdome is your part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Loath was the Ape (though praiſed) to aduenture,</l>
               <l>Yet faintly gan into his worke to enter,</l>
               <l>Afraid of cuery leafe that ſtirr'd him by,</l>
               <l>And euery ſtick that vnderneath did ly;</l>
               <l>Vpon his tiptoes nicely he vp went,</l>
               <l>For making noyſe, and ſtill his eare he lent</l>
               <l>To euery ſound, that vnder heauen blew,</l>
               <l>Now went, now ſtept, now crept, now backward drew,</l>
               <l>That it good ſport had beene him to haue eyde:</l>
               <l>Yet at the laſt (ſo well he him applyde,)</l>
               <l>Through his fine handling, and his cleanly play,</l>
               <l>He all thoſe royall ſignes had ſtolne away,</l>
               <l>And with the Foxes helpe them borne aſide,</l>
               <l>Into a ſecret corner vneſpide.</l>
               <l>Whither when as they came, they fell at words,</l>
               <l>Whether of them ſhould be the Lord of Lords:</l>
               <l>For th' Ape was ſtryfefull, and ambicious;</l>
               <l>And the Foxe guilefull, and moſt couetous,</l>
               <l>That neither pleaſed was, to haue the raine</l>
               <l>Twixt them diuided into euen twaine,</l>
               <l>But either (algates) would be Lords alone:</l>
               <l>For Loue and Lordſhip bide no paragone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I am moſt worthy (ſaid the Ape) ſith I</l>
               <l>For it did put my life in ieopardy:</l>
               <l>There-to I am in perſon and in ſtature</l>
               <l>Moſt like a man, the Lord of euery creature,</l>
               <l>So that it ſeemeth I was made to raigne,</l>
               <l>And borne to be a kingly Soueraigne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay (ſaid the Foxe) Sir Ape you are aſtray:</l>
               <l>For though to ſteale the Diademe away</l>
               <l>Were the worke of your nimble hand, yet I</l>
               <l>Did firſt deuiſe the plot by policie;</l>
               <l>So that it wholly ſpringeth from my wit:</l>
               <l>For which alſo I claime my ſelfe more fit</l>
               <l>Than you, to rule<hi>:</hi> for gouernment of ſtate</l>
               <l>Will without wiſedome ſoone be ruinate.</l>
               <l>And where you claime your ſelfe for outward ſhape</l>
               <l>Moſt like a man, Man is not like an Ape</l>
               <l>In his chiefe parts, that is, in wit and ſpirit;</l>
               <l>But I therein moſt like to him doe merite</l>
               <l>For my ſlie wyles and ſubtill craftineſſe,</l>
               <l>The title of the kingdome to poſſeſſe.</l>
               <l>Nath'leſſe (my brother) ſince we paſſed are</l>
               <l>Vnto this poynt, we will appeaſe our iarre,</l>
               <l>And I with reaſon meet will reſt content,</l>
               <l>That ye ſhall haue both crowne and gouernment,</l>
               <l>Vpon condition, that ye ruled bee</l>
               <l>In all affaires, and counſelled by me;</l>
               <l>And that ye let none other euer drawe</l>
               <l>Your minde from mee, but keepe this as a law:</l>
               <l>And hereupon an oath vnto me plight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Ape was glad to end the ſtrife ſo light,</l>
               <l>And there-to ſwore: for who would not oft ſweare,</l>
               <l>And oft vnſweare, a Diademe to beare?</l>
               <l>Then freely vp thoſe royall ſpoyles he tooke,</l>
               <l>Yet at the Lions skin he inly quooke;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:26504:8"/> But it diſſembled, and vpon his head</l>
               <l>The Crowne, and on his backe the skin he did,</l>
               <l>And the falſe Foxe him helped to array.</l>
               <l>Then when he was all dight, he tooke his way</l>
               <l>Into the forreſt, that he might be ſeene</l>
               <l>Of the wilde beaſts in his new glory ſheene.</l>
               <l>There the two firſt, whom he encountred, were</l>
               <l>The Sheepe and th' Aſſe, who ſtriken both with feare</l>
               <l>At ſight of him, gan faſt away to flye,</l>
               <l>But vnto them the Foxe aloud did cry,</l>
               <l>And in the Kings name bad them both to ſtay,</l>
               <l>Vpon the paine that thereof follow may.</l>
               <l>Hardly nath' leſſe were they reſtrained ſo,</l>
               <l>Till that the Foxe forth toward them did go,</l>
               <l>And there diſſwaded them from needleſſe feare,</l>
               <l>For that the King did fauour to them beare;</l>
               <l>And therefore dreadleſſe bad them come to
Corte<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For no wilde beaſts ſhould doe them any torte</l>
               <l>There or abroad, ne would his maieſtie</l>
               <l>Vſe them but well; with gracious clemencie,</l>
               <l>As whom he knew to him both faſt and true;</l>
               <l>So he perſwaded them with homage due</l>
               <l>Themſelues to humble to the Ape proſtrate,</l>
               <l>Who gently to them bowing in his gate,</l>
               <l>Receiued them with chearefull entertaine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thence, forth proceeding with his princely traine,</l>
               <l>He ſhortly met the Tygre, and the Bore,</l>
               <l>Which with the ſimple Camell raged ſore</l>
               <l>In bitter words, ſeeking to take occaſion,</l>
               <l>Vpon his fleſhy corps to make inuaſion:</l>
               <l>But ſoone as they this mock-King did eſpy,</l>
               <l>Their troublous ſtrife they ſtinted by and by,</l>
               <l>Thinking indeed that it the Lion was.</l>
               <l>He then to proue whether his power would paſſe</l>
               <l>As currant, ſent the Foxe to them ſtraight way,</l>
               <l>Commaunding them their cauſe of ſtrife bewray;</l>
               <l>And if that wrong on either ſide there were,</l>
               <l>That he ſhould warne the wronger to appeare</l>
               <l>The morrow next at Court, it to defend;</l>
               <l>In the meane time vpon the King t' attend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The ſubtile Foxe ſo well his meſſage ſaid,</l>
               <l>That the proud beaſts him readily obayd:</l>
               <l>Whereby th' Ape in wondrous ſtomack woxe,</l>
               <l>Strongly encourag'd by the crafty Foxe;</l>
               <l>That King indeed himſelfe he ſhortly thought,</l>
               <l>And all the beaſts him feared as they ought:</l>
               <l>And followed vnto his Palace hie,</l>
               <l>Where taking Conge, each one by and by</l>
               <l>Departed to his home in dreadfull awe,</l>
               <l>Full of the feared ſight which late they ſawe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Ape thus ſeized of the Regall throne,</l>
               <l>Eftſoones by counſell of the Foxe alone,</l>
               <l>Gan to prouide for all things in aſſurance,</l>
               <l>That ſo his rule might lenger haue endurance.</l>
               <l>Firſt, to his Gate he pointed a ſtrong gard,</l>
               <l>That none might enter but with iſſue hard:</l>
               <l>Then for the ſafegard of his perſonage,</l>
               <l>He did appoint a warlike equipage</l>
               <l>Of forraine beaſts, not in the forreſt bred,</l>
               <l>But part by land, and part by water fed;</l>
               <l>For tyrannie is with ſtrange ayde ſupported.</l>
               <l>Then vnto him all monſtrous beaſts reſorted</l>
               <l>Bred of two kindes, as Griffons, Minotaures,</l>
               <l>Crocodiles, Dragons, Beauers, and Centaures:</l>
               <l>With thoſe himſelfe he ſtrengthned mightily,</l>
               <l>That feare he neede no force of enemy.</l>
               <l>Then gan he rule and tyrannize at will,</l>
               <l>Like as the Foxe did guide his graceleſſe skill,</l>
               <l>And all wilde beaſts made vaſſals of his pleaſures,</l>
               <l>And with their ſpoyles enlarg'd his priuate treaſures.</l>
               <l>No care of iuſtice, nor no rule of reaſon,</l>
               <l>No temperance, nor no regard of ſeaſon</l>
               <l>Did thenceforth euer enter in his minde,</l>
               <l>But crueltie, the ſigne of curriſh kinde,</l>
               <l>And ſdeignfull pride, and wilfull arrogance;</l>
               <l>Such followes thoſe whom fortune doth aduance.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But the falſe Foxe moſt kindly plaid his part:</l>
               <l>For, whatſoeuer mother wit, or arte</l>
               <l>Could worke, he put in proofe: no practiſe ſlie,</l>
               <l>No counterpoint of cunning policie,</l>
               <l>No reach, no breach, that might him profit bring,</l>
               <l>But he the ſame did to his purpoſe wring.</l>
               <l>Nought ſuffered he the Ape to giue or grant,</l>
               <l>But through his hand muſt paſſe the Fiant.</l>
               <l>All offices, all Leaſes by him lept,</l>
               <l>And of them all what-ſo he likte, he kept.</l>
               <l>Iuſtice he ſolde iniuſtice for to buy,</l>
               <l>And for to purchaſe for his progeny.</l>
               <l>Ill might it proſper, that ill gotten was:</l>
               <l>But ſo he got it, little did he paſſe.</l>
               <l>He fed his cubs with fat of all the ſoyle,</l>
               <l>And with the ſweet of others ſweating toyle,</l>
               <l>He crammed them with crums of Benefices,</l>
               <l>And fild their mouthes with meeds of malefices,</l>
               <l>He cloathed them with all colours ſaue white,</l>
               <l>And loaded them with Lordſhips and with might,</l>
               <l>So much as they were able well to beare,</l>
               <l>That with the weight their backs nigh broken were;</l>
               <l>He chaffred Chayres in which Churchmen were ſet,</l>
               <l>And breach of lawes to priuie ferme did let.</l>
               <l>No ſtatute ſo eſtabliſhed might be,</l>
               <l>Nor ordinance ſo needfull, but that he</l>
               <l>Would violate, though not with violence,</l>
               <l>Yet vnder colour of the confidence</l>
               <l>The which the Ape repos'd in him alone,</l>
               <l>And reckned him the kingdoms corner-ſtone.</l>
               <l>And euer when he ought would bring to paſſe,</l>
               <l>His long experience the platforme was<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And when he ought not pleaſing would put by,</l>
               <l>The clocke was care of thrift, and husbandry,</l>
               <l>For to encreaſe the common treaſures ſtore;</l>
               <l>But his owne treaſure he encreaſed more,</l>
               <l>And lifted vp his lofty towres therby,</l>
               <l>That they began to threat the neighbour sky;</l>
               <l>The whiles the Princes Palaces fell faſt</l>
               <l>To ruine: (for what thing can euer laſt?)</l>
               <l>And whil'ſt the other Peeres for pouertie</l>
               <l>Were forc't their auncient houſes to let lie,</l>
               <l>And their old Caſtles to the ground to fall,</l>
               <l>Which their forefathers (famous ouer all)</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:26504:8"/> Had founded for the Kingdoms ornament,</l>
               <l>And for their memories long monument.</l>
               <l>But he no count made of Nobilitie,</l>
               <l>Nor the wilde beaſts whom armes did glorifie,</l>
               <l>The Realmes chiefe ſtrength and girlond of the Crowne;</l>
               <l>All theſe through fained crimes he thruſt a downe,</l>
               <l>Or made them dwell in darknes of diſgrace:</l>
               <l>For none, but whom he liſt might come in place.</l>
               <l>Of men of armes he had but ſmall regard,</l>
               <l>But kept them lowe, and ſtreightned very hard<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For men of learning little he eſteemed;</l>
               <l>His wiſedome he aboue their learning deemed.</l>
               <l>As for the raſcall Commons leaſt he cared;</l>
               <l>For not ſo common was his bounty ſhared;</l>
               <l>Let God (ſaid he) if pleaſe, care for the many,</l>
               <l>I for my ſelfe muſt care before elſe any:</l>
               <l>So did he good to none, to many ill,</l>
               <l>So did he all the kingdome rob and pill,</l>
               <l>Yet none durſt ſpeake, nor none durſt of him plaine;</l>
               <l>So great he was in grace, and rich through gaine.</l>
               <l>Ne would he any let to haue acceſſe</l>
               <l>Vnto the Prince, but by his owne addreſſe<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For all that elſe did come, were ſure to faile,</l>
               <l>Yet would he further none but for availe.</l>
               <l>For, on a time the Sheepe, to whom of yore</l>
               <l>The Foxe had promiſed of friendſhip ſtore,</l>
               <l>What time the Ape the kingdome firſt did gaine,</l>
               <l>Came to the Court, her caſe there to complaine,</l>
               <l>How that the Wolfe her mortall enemie,</l>
               <l>Had ſithence ſlaine her Lambe moſt cruelly;</l>
               <l>And therefore crau'd to come vnto the King,</l>
               <l>To let him know the order of the thing.</l>
               <l>Soft gooddy Sheepe (then ſaid the Foxe) not ſo:</l>
               <l>Vnto the King ſo raſh ye may not goe,</l>
               <l>He is with greater matter buſied,</l>
               <l>Then a Lamb, or the Lambs owne mothers hed,</l>
               <l>Ne certes may I take it well in part,</l>
               <l>That ye my couſin Wolfe ſo fouly thwart,</l>
               <l>And ſeeke with ſlander his good name to blot:</l>
               <l>For there was cauſe, elſe doe it he would not.</l>
               <l>Therefore ſurceaſe good Dame, and hence depart,</l>
               <l>So went the Sheepe away with heauie heart.</l>
               <l>So many moe, ſo euery one was vſed,</l>
               <l>That to giue largely to the boxe refuſed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now when high <hi>loue,</hi> in whoſe almighty hand</l>
               <l>The care of Kings, and power of Empires ſtand,</l>
               <l>Sitting one day within his turret hie,</l>
               <l>From whence he viewes with his black-lidded eye,</l>
               <l>What-ſo the heauen in his wide vawte containes,</l>
               <l>And all that in the deepeſt earth remaines,</l>
               <l>And troubled kingdome of wilde beaſts beheld,</l>
               <l>Whom not their kindly Souereigne did weld,</l>
               <l>But an vſurping Ape with guile ſuborn'd,</l>
               <l>Had all ſubuerſt, he ſdeignfully it ſcorn'd,</l>
               <l>In his great hart, and hardly did refraine,</l>
               <l>But that with thunder-bolts he had him ſlaine,</l>
               <l>And driuen down to hell, his deweſt meed<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But him avizing, he that dreadfull deed</l>
               <l>Forbore, and rather choſe with ſcornfull ſhame</l>
               <l>Him to auenge, and blot his brutiſh name</l>
               <l>Vnto the world, that neuer after any</l>
               <l>Should of his race be voyd of infamy:</l>
               <l>And his falſe counſellor, the cauſe of all,</l>
               <l>To damne to death, or dole perpetuall,</l>
               <l>From whence he neuer ſhould be quit, not ſtall'd.</l>
               <l>Forth-with he <hi>Mercurie</hi> vnto him call'd,</l>
               <l>And bad him flie with neuer-reſting ſpeed</l>
               <l>Vnto the forreſt, where wilde beaſts doe breed,</l>
               <l>And there enquiring priuily, to learne,</l>
               <l>What did of late chance to the Lion ſtearne,</l>
               <l>That he rul'd not the Empire, as he ought;</l>
               <l>And whence were all thoſe plaints vnto him brought</l>
               <l>Of wrongs and ſpoiles, by ſaluage beaſts committed;</l>
               <l>Which done he bad the Lion be remitted</l>
               <l>Into his ſeat, and thoſe ſame treachours vile</l>
               <l>Be puniſhed for their preſumptuous guile.</l>
               <l>The ſonne of <hi>Maia</hi> ſoone as he receiu'd</l>
               <l>The word, ſtraight with his azure wings he cleau'd</l>
               <l>The liquid clowdes, and lucid firmament;</l>
               <l>Ne ſtaid, till that he came with ſleepe deſcent</l>
               <l>Vnto the place, where his preſcript did ſhowe.</l>
               <l>There ſtouping like an arrowe from a bowe,</l>
               <l>He ſoft arriued on the graffie Plaine,</l>
               <l>And fairely paſſed forth with eaſie paine,</l>
               <l>Till that vnto the Palace nigh he came.</l>
               <l>Then gau hee to himſelfe new ſhape to frame,</l>
               <l>And that faire face, and that Ambroſiall hew</l>
               <l>Which wonts to decke the Gods immortall crew,</l>
               <l>And beautifie the ſhinie firmament,</l>
               <l>He doft, vnfit for that rude rabblement.</l>
               <l>So ſtanding by the gates in ſtrange diſguize,</l>
               <l>He gan enquire of ſome in ſecret wize,</l>
               <l>Both of the King and of his gouernment,</l>
               <l>And of the Foxe, and his falſe blandiſhment:</l>
               <l>And euermore he heard each one complaine</l>
               <l>Of foule abuſes both in realme and raigne.</l>
               <l>Which yet to proue more true, he meant to ſee,</l>
               <l>And an eye-witnes of each thing to bee.</l>
               <l>Tho, on his head his dreadfull hat he dight,</l>
               <l>Which maketh him inuiſible in ſight,</l>
               <l>And mocketh th' eyes of all the lookers on,</l>
               <l>Making them thinke it but a viſion.</l>
               <l>Through power of that, he runnes through enemies ſwerds;</l>
               <l>Through power of that, he paſſeth through the herds</l>
               <l>Of rauenous wilde beaſts, and doth beguile</l>
               <l>Their greedie mouthes of the expected ſpoile;</l>
               <l>Through power of that, his cunning theeueries</l>
               <l>He wonts to worke, that none the ſame eſpies;</l>
               <l>And through the power of that, he putteth on,</l>
               <l>What ſhape he liſt in apparition.</l>
               <l>That on his head he wore: and in his hand</l>
               <l>He tooke <hi>Caduceus</hi> his ſnakie wand,</l>
               <l>With which the damned ghoſts he gouerneth,</l>
               <l>And furies rules, and Tartare tempereth.</l>
               <l>With that he cauſeth ſleepe to ſeize the eyes,</l>
               <l>And fear the harts of all his enemies;</l>
               <l>And when he liſt, an vniuerſall night</l>
               <l>Throughout the world he makes on euery wight<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>As when his Sire with <hi>Alcumena</hi> lay.</l>
               <l>Thus dight, into the Court he tooke his way,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:26504:9"/> Both through the gard, which neuer him
deſcride,</l>
               <l>And through the watch-men, who him neuer ſpide:</l>
               <l>Thence, forth he paſt into each ſecret part,</l>
               <l>Where-as he ſaw (that ſorely grieu'd his heart)</l>
               <l>Each place abounding with foule iniuries,</l>
               <l>And fild with treaſure rackt with robberies:</l>
               <l>Each place defilde with blood of guiltleſſe beaſts,</l>
               <l>Which had beene ſlaine to ſerue the Apes beheaſts;</l>
               <l>Gluttony, malice, pride, and couetize,</l>
               <l>And lawleſnes raigning with riotize;</l>
               <l>Beſides the infinite extortions,</l>
               <l>Done through the Foxes great oppreſſions,</l>
               <l>That the complaints thereof could not be tolde.</l>
               <l>Which when he did with lothfull eyes behold,</l>
               <l>He would no more endure, but came his way,</l>
               <l>And caſt to ſeeke the Lion where he may,</l>
               <l>That he might worke the auengement for this ſhame,</l>
               <l>On thoſe two caytiues, which had bred him blame.</l>
               <l>And ſeeking all the forreſt buſily,</l>
               <l>At laſt he found, where ſleeping he did ly:</l>
               <l>The wicked weed, which there the Foxe did lay,</l>
               <l>From underneath his head he tooke away,</l>
               <l>And then him waking, forced vp to rize.</l>
               <l>The Lion looking vp, gan him avize,</l>
               <l>As one late in a traunce, what had of long</l>
               <l>Become of him: for fantaſie is ſtrong.</l>
               <l>Ariſe (ſaid <hi>Mercurie)</hi> thou ſluggiſh
beaſt,</l>
               <l>That heere lieſt ſenſeleſſe, like the corpſe
deceaſt,</l>
               <l>The whil'ſt thy kingdome from thy head is rent,</l>
               <l>And thy throne royall with diſhonor blent:</l>
               <l>Ariſe, and doe thy ſelfe redeeme from ſhame,</l>
               <l>And be aueng'd on thoſe that breed thy blame.</l>
               <l>There-at enraged, ſoone he gan vp-ſtart,</l>
               <l>Grinding his teeth, and grating his great heart,</l>
               <l>And rouzing vp himſelfe, for his rough hide</l>
               <l>He gan to reach; but no where it eſpide.</l>
               <l>There-with he gan full terribly to rore,</l>
               <l>And chauft at that indignity right ſore.</l>
               <l>But when his Crowne and Scepter both he wanted</l>
               <l>Lord how he fum'd, and ſweld, and rag'd, and panted;</l>
               <l>And threatned death, and thouſand deadly dolours</l>
               <l>To them that had purloyn'd his Princely honours!</l>
               <l>With that in haſte, diſroabed as he was,</l>
               <l>He toward his owne Palace forth did paſſe;</l>
               <l>And all the way he roared as he went,</l>
               <l>That all the forreſt with aſtoniſhment</l>
               <l>Thereof did tremble, and the beaſts therein</l>
               <l>Fled faſt away from that ſo dreadfull din.</l>
               <l>At laſt, he came vnto his manſion,</l>
               <l>Where all the gates he found faſt lockt anon,</l>
               <l>And many warders round about them ſtood.</l>
               <l>With that he roar'd aloud, as he were wood,</l>
               <l>That all the Palace quaked at the ſtound,</l>
               <l>As if it quite were riuen from the ground,</l>
               <l>And all within were dead and hartleſſe left;</l>
               <l>And th' Ape himſelfe, as one whoſe wits were reft,</l>
               <l>Fled heere and there, and euery corner ſought,</l>
               <l>To hide himſelfe from his owne feared thought.</l>
               <l>But the falſe Foxe, when he the Lion heard,</l>
               <l>Fled cloſely forth, ſtraight-way of death afeard,</l>
               <l>And to the Lion came full lowly creeping,</l>
               <l>With fained face, and watry eyne halfe weeping,</l>
               <l>T' excuſe his former treaſon and abuſion,</l>
               <l>And turning all vnto the Apes confuſion:</l>
               <l>Nath'leſſe, the royall Beaſt for bore beleeuing,</l>
               <l>But bad him ſtay at eaſe till further preeuing.</l>
               <l>Then when he ſaw no entrance to him graunted,</l>
               <l>Roaring yet lowder that all harts it daunted,</l>
               <l>Vpon thoſe gates with force he fiercely flew,</l>
               <l>And rending them in peeces, felly ſlew</l>
               <l>Thoſe warders ſtrange, and all that elſe he met,</l>
               <l>But th' Ape ſtill flying, he no where might get<hi>:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From roume to roume, from beame to beame he fled</l>
               <l>All breathleſſe, and for feare now almoſt ded:</l>
               <l>Yet him at laſt the Lion ſpide and caught,</l>
               <l>And forth with ſhame vnto his iudgement brought.</l>
               <l>Then all the beaſts he caus'd aſſembled be,</l>
               <l>To heare their doome, and ſad enſample ſee.</l>
               <l>The Foxe, firſt Author of that treacherie,</l>
               <l>He did vncaſe, and then abroad let flie.</l>
               <l>But th' Apes long taile (which then he had) he quight</l>
               <l>Cut off, and both eares pared of their hight;</l>
               <l>Since which, all Apes but halfe their eares haue left,</l>
               <l>And of their tailes are vtterly bereft.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So Mother <hi>Hubberd</hi> her diſcourſe did end:</l>
               <l>Which pardon me, if I a miſſe haue pend;</l>
               <l>For, weake was my remembrance it to hold,</l>
               <l>And bad her tongue that it ſo bluntly told.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26504:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
